A Guide to the Papers of the Norfolk Branch of the American Association of University Women 1902-2000
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
The Papers of the Norfolk Branch of the American Association of University Women 1902-2000
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 74
11 linear feet, 13 document cases and 9 oversized boxes.
Administrative Information
Access
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mary Wright Thrasher, March 2000. Accession #: A2000-4
Biographical/Historical Information
The roots of the Norfolk branch of the American Association of University Women (AAUW) can be traced to December 10, 1902, when ten women met in Norfolk, Virginia. to form the College Club of Norfolk. The purpose of this group was to support higher education for women. The requirement for membership was a minimum of one year of college at any Association of Collegiate Alumnae (ACA) approved college. In 1918 the College Club of Norfolk united with the Southern Association of College Women (SACW) and became part of the AAUW as a result of the 1921 merge of the SACW and the ACA. In 1922 the first national convention of the AAUW was held in Kansas City, Missouri and a representative from the Norfolk branch was in attendance.
One of first projects the branch, was creating a scholarship for women to attend an approved college. In 1909 Miss Nettie Sterling of Gloucester, Virginia received the first scholarship. In 1922 Miss Cherry Nottingham, referred to as the "Branch's intellectual core," joined the AAUW and in later years this scholarship became known as the Cherry Nottingham scholarship.
In the 1920s the Norfolk branch of the AAUW joined national AAUW efforts to purchase a gram of radium to present to Madame Curie as a gift of American women on the occasion of Curie's visit to the United States.
The Norfolk branch of the AAUW was among the first racially integrated women's organizations.
Other major interests of the branch over the years have been pre-schools, nurseries, daycare centers, poverty, school integration, civil rights, and international relations.
Men are also admitted to the Norfolk branch of the AAUW on the basis of their educational qualifications.
Scope and Content Information
The Papers of the Norfolk branch of the American Association of University Women date from 1902 to 2000. The collection includes information about the history and organization of the group, meeting minutes, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, conference brochures, branch reports, and other publications by and about the group. The bulk of the collection is in the following categories: history, meeting minutes, reports, scrapbooks, and publications.
Organization
The collection is comprised of the following twelve series: I. History; II. Organization; III. Minutes; IV. Reports; V. Issues/Activities; VI. Annual Conventions; VII. Handbooks; VIII. Yearbooks; IX. Publications; X. Miscellaneous; XI. Promotional Materials; XII. Scrapbooks.
Series I: History: This series is divided into two subseries. Subseries A: National; Subseries B: Norfolk Branch.
Subseries A: National. This subseries contains publications and a cassette recording about the creation and growth of the American Association of University Women from 1881 to 1981. Included is material from the 75th and centennial anniversaries.
Subseries B: Norfolk Branch. This subseries contains publications, notes, photographs, and a cassette recording about the history of the Norfolk Branch of the AAUW from 1902 to 2000.
Series II: Organization: This series is divided into three sub-series. Subseries A: Members; Subseries B: Bylaws & Policies; Subseries C: Finances.
Subseries A: Members. This subseries contains lists of chapter members and branch officers from various decades.
Subseries B: Bylaws & Policies. This subseries describes responsibilities, duties, and policies involved with being an AAUW member or officer.
Subseries C: Finances. The bulk of the material in this series is from the 1980s. Treasurer's Reports from the 1940s may also be found interfiled with the Meeting Minutes from the 1940s.
Series III: Minutes: This series is divided into two subseries and contains minutes of the AAUW meetings dating back to the organization's beginning in 1902. The minutes provide details of the meetings and daily activities of the organization. Minutes are handwritten, typed, and composed on a word processor. Some of the minutes folders, especially from the 1940s, have Treasurer's reports interfiled.
Subseries A: Minutes Books. This subseries consists of four minutes books covering 1902-1939. Each book is fragile and must be handled with care. These minute books are in box 22.
Subseries B: Minutes Folders. This subseries consists of minutes from 1939 to the 1990s.
Series IV: Reports: The bulk of this series contains annual branch reports from the 1940s and 1980s. Also included are folders titled Committee Reports 1938-1939 and President's Report 1945.
Series V: Issues/Activities: This series describes issues and activities focused upon by the AAUW such as education, daycare, and poverty. Information about some issues is located in other places throughout the collection such as in the minutes or miscellaneous folders. Particularly noteworthy issues throughout the AAUW are the Cherry Nottingham Scholarship and the Antiques Fair.
Subseries A: Scholarships. This subseries provides information about the Cherry Nottingham Scholarship, one of the first activities of the Norfolk branch of the AAUW, and a book on the history of the Fellowship Program of the AAUW titled "Investment in Creative Scholarship" by Ruth W. Tryon.
Subseries B: 7th Annual Antiques Fair 1956. This subseries contains materials removed from a scrapbook about the 7th annual Antiques Fair. The Antiques Fair was one of the branch's biggest fundraisers. Funds raised were used for the Cherry Nottingham Scholarship. Other materials related to the Antiques Fair can be found in Series XII: Scrapbooks.
Subseries C: Other Issues/Activities. This subseries contains information about issues considered important to the branch. Such issues are daycare, fundraising, ERA, and the development of Norfolk. Materials related to this subseries can be found in Series III: Minutes and Series X: Miscellaneous.
Series VI: Annual Conventions: This series contains brochures from the annual conventions. The bulk of the material is from the 1980s and 1990s.
Series VII: Handbooks: The Handbooks contain information about branch members, a calendar of events, and updates regarding scholarship recipients. This series contains Handbooks from the 1970s-2000. The handbooks may be successors of the Yearbooks.
Series VIII: Yearbooks: The Yearbooks are similar in format and content to the Handbooks and may be predecessors of the Handbooks. The Yearbooks contain information about branch members, a calendar of events, and updates regarding membership dues. This series contains Yearbooks from the 1950s and 1960s.
Series IX: Publications: This series contains monographs and serial publications by and about the AAUW, both nationally and locally. "AAUW News" is the first newsletter of the Norfolk Branch dating back to the 1950s. This publication undergoes several design, frequency, and numbering changes; however, this publication offers a close look into the activities of the Norfolk branch of the AAUW. Both the Fall 1981 and the Winter 1981 issues of "Leader in Action" are labeled v.1 no.1; however, the Fall 1981 issue states that it is the premiere issue. "Outlook" is published by the AAUW and distributed free of charge to all AAUW members.
Series X: Miscellaneous: This series contains materials from the 1950s through the 1990s. Materials include newspaper clippings, photographs, and research materials related to topics in Series V, Subseries C: Other Issues/Activities.
Series XI: Promotional Materials: This series consists of AAUW stationery, letterhead, and merchandise catalogs.
Series XII: Scrapbooks: This series is divided into two subseries. Subseries A: General Scrapbooks; Subseries B: Antiques Fair Scrapbooks.
Subseries A: General Scrapbooks. This bulk of this subseries consists of scrapbooks from the 1950s.
Subseries B: Antiques Fair Scrapbooks. This subseries consists of two scrapbooks devoted to the Antiques Fair. Materials from a third Antiques Fair scrapbook were removed from the scrapbook and are housed in Box 5, Subseries B: 7th Annual Antiques Fair. The scrapbook in subseries A: General Scrapbooks dated 1949-1950 contains some Antiques Fair information.
Contents List
- History
  - National
    - "AAUW 1881-1949" by Ruth W. Tryon (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "AAUW 1882-1957" Seventy-Fifth Anniversary (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "AAUW 1881-1981" Centennial Celebration (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Centennial Audio Tapes, 1881-1981 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "The Talbot Story...A Play In Three Acts" (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Norfolk Branch
    - Decade of the Virginia Division, 1960-1970 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Fact Sheet (1990s) (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "The History of the Virginia Division," 1960 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 60th Anniversary of the Norfolk Branch with the Portsmouth Branch, 1962 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 75th Anniversary of the Norfolk Branch, 1977 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 75th Anniversary of the Norfolk Branch: Audio Tape, December 3, 1977 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Norfolk Division History, 1997 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 13)
- Organization
  - Members
    - Branch Officers, 1946-1953 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Branch Officers, 1985/1986-1989/1990 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Branch Officers (Other Virginia Chapters) (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Dossier of Missing Fellows List, 1987 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Membership, 1935-1939 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Membership List-1990s (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 19)
    - New/Prospective Members (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bylaws and Policies
    - Bylaws and Policies-1970s (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Bylaws and Policies-1980s (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Bylaws and Policies-1990s (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Duties of Officers (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Leadership (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Membership (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Parliamentary Procedure (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Resolutions (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Finances
    - Donations (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Dues Reports, 1981-1982 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Treasurer, 1958 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Treasurer-1970s (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Treasurer, 1980-1985 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Treasurer, 1985-1990 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Treasurer-1990s (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 12)
- Minutes
  - Minutes, October 1939-September 1945 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, October 1945-May 1949 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1949-1953 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1953-1954 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, June 1953-May 1955 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1985 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1986 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, 1987 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1988-1989 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Minutes-1990s (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 10)
- Branch Reports
  - Branch Reports, 1940/1941 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Branch Reports, 1941/1942 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Branch Reports, 1942/1943 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Branch Reports, 1944/1945-1945/1946 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Branch Reports, 1947/1948 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Branch Reports, 1950/1951-1951/1952 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Branch Reports, 1980/1981 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Branch Reports, 1984 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Branch Reports, 1985 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Branch Reports, 1986 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Branch Reports, 1986/1987 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Branch Reports, 1987 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Committee Reports, 1938/1939 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 13)
  - President's Report, 1945 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 14)
  - President's Report, 1995/1996 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 15)
- Issues/Activities
  - Scholarships
    - Cherry Nottingham Scholarship (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Fellowship Program: "Investment in Creative Scholarship 1890-1956," by Ruth W. Tryon (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 7th Annual Antiques Fair, 1956
    - Address Lists (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Announcement (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Application for State License, Insurance Policy (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Applications for Booths (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Bill (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Fair Management (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Fashion Show (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Instructions for Exhibitors (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Letters to Ticket Chairmen (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Opening Ceremonies (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Papers for Arena Rental (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Poster (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Program (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Programs from Other Antique Shows (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Publicity-Broadcast Media (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Publicity-Print Media (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Publicity-Window Displays (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Recommendations (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Register of Visitors (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Report of the Finance Chairman, 1956 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Report of the Tea Room Chairman (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Statements (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Stationery (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Tea Room Catering (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Other Issues/Activities
    - Contributions (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Directory of Nursery and Kindergartens in Norfolk, Virginia, October 1963 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 2)
    - ERA (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Fundraising (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Fundraising Handbook (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Grants (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 6)
    - International Federation of University Women (IFUW) (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Norfolk Redevelopment and Housing Edition (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Pay Equity (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Poverty (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Programs 1936/1937-1940/1941 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Program Planning (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Public Support/Public Education (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Tokyo Women's College (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Town Meeting on Norfolk's Future, November 1982 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 15)
    - "Woman of Achievement-1978," nomination (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Women's Work/Women's Inventory (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 17)
- Annual Conventions
  - Virginia Division 23rd Annual Convention, April 16-17, 1948 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Division 51st Annual Convention, April 2-4, 1976 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Division 55th Annual Convention, April 11-13, 1980 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Division 23rd Annual Convention, April 27-29, 1981 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Division 57th Annual Convention, April 30-May 2, 1982 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Division 59th Annual Convention, April 27-29, 1984 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Division 60th Annual Convention, April 26-28, 1985 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Division 62nd Annual Convention, April 24-26, 1987 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Division 66th Annual Convention, April 19-21, 1991 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Division 67th Annual Convention, May 1-3, 1992 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Division 69th Annual Convention, April 23, 1994 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Division 70th Annual Convention, April 28-30, 1995 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 12)
- Handbooks
  - Handbooks, 1970/1971-1979/1980 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Handbooks, 1980/1981-1989/1990 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Handbooks, 1990/1991-1999/2000 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 3)
- Yearbooks
  - Yearbooks, 1951/1952-1959/1960 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Yearbooks, 1960/1961-1969/1970 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 5)
- Publications
  - "AAUW Assignment in Human Freedom," 1949 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 1)
  - "AAUW Branch Leadership Handbook," 1977 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 2)
  - "AAUW Branch Leaders Handbook," 1982 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 3)
  - "AAUW Branch Leaders Handbook," 1984 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 4)
  - "AAUW Investments Unlimited News," 1957 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 5)
  - "AAUW Legislative History and Policy Notes," 1981-1983 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 6)
  - "AAUW News" (title changes to AAUW Bulletin), 1950-1961 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 7)
  - "AAUW Bulletin" (title changes to Norfolk Branch Bulletin), 1961-1962 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 8)
  - "Norfolk Branch Bulletin," 1964-1968 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 9)
  - "Norfolk Branch Bulletin," 1968-1976 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 10)
  - "Norfolk Branch Bulletin," 1976-1986 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 11)
  - "Norfolk Branch Bulletin," 1994-1996 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 12)
  - "Graduate Women" (v.77 no.4-v.77 no.7), July/August-November/December 1983 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 1)
  - "Graduate Women" January 1984 (v.78 no.1), March-June 1984 (v.78 no.3-v.78 no.6), September-October 1984 (v.78 no.8-v.78 no.9) (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 2)
  - "Graduate Women" (v.79 no.1), January 1985 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 3)
  - "Graduate Women" (v.80 no.5-v.80 no.8), June-November/December 1986 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 4)
  - "Graduate Women" (v.81 no.1-v.81 no.6), January/February-November/December 1987 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 5)
  - "Graduate Women" (v.82 no.1-v.82 no.3), January/February-May/June 1988 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 6)
  - "Leader in Action," Winter 1981-Spring 1993 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Newsletters from other Virginia Chapters (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 8)
  - "Outlook," 1993-1996 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 1)
  - "Virginia Division Bulletin," 1942-1948 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 2)
  - "Virginia Division Bulletin," 1949-1954 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 3)
  - "Virginia Division Bulletin," 1954-1965 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 4)
  - "Virginia Division Bulletin," 1965-1975 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 5)
  - "Virginia Division Bulletin," 1975-1983 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 6)
  - "Virginia Division Bulletin," 1983-1984 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 7)
  - "Virginia Division Bulletin," 1984-1986 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 8)
  - "Virginia Vision," 1987-1988 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 9)
  - "Virginia Vision," 1992-1994, 1996, 2000 (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous
  - 1950s Miscellaneous (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 1)
  - 1950s Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 2)
  - 1960s Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 3)
  - 1970s Miscellaneous (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 4)
  - 1970s Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings (I) (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 5)
  - 1970s Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings (II) (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1970-1980 (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 7)
  - 1980s Miscellaneous (I) (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 8)
  - 1980s Miscellaneous (II) (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 9)
  - 1980s Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 10)
  - 1980s Miscellaneous Photographs (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1982-1983 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1983-1984 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1984-1985 (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 3)
  - 1990s Miscellaneous (I) (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 4)
  - 1990s Miscellaneous (II) (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 5)
- Promotional Materials
  - Available Materials (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Letterhead (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Merchandise Catalogs (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Stationery (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 9)
- Scrapbooks
  - General Scrapbooks
    - 1949-1950 (Box Box 14)
    - 1951-1952 (Box Box 15)
    - 1954-1955 (two scrapbooks) (Box Box 16)
    - 1955-1956, 1956-1957 (Box Box 17)
    - 1957-1958 (Box Box 18)
    - 1969-1970 (Box Box 19)
  - Antiques Fair Scrapbooks
    - 1953, 1955 (Box Box 20)
    - The contents of the scrapbook in this box are housed in Box 5, Subseries B: 7th Annual Antiques Fair-1956 (Box Box 21)
    - The contents of this box are the four minutes books from Subseries A: Minutes Books (Box Box 22)